非洲
Africa.
这里拥有地球上最为雄浑壮丽的野生奇观
No continent on Earth today has such spectacular wildlife.
它的中心是郁郁葱葱的广阔热带雨林
At its heart lies a vast tropical rainforest.
超过200万平方公里的旷野，
Over a million square miles of wilderness,
其中大部分是仍未开发的原始森林
much of it still unexplored...
...even now.
这些丛林中有更多种类的动植物
There are more species of animals and plants in these jungles
比非洲大陆其他任何地方都重要
than anywhere else on the continent.
但是即使在这片土地上
But even in this land of plenty...
野生动物正在面临着许多严峻挑战
...wildlife now faces major challenges.
象牙海岸（科特迪瓦）的森林
The forests of the Ivory Coast
包含超过1,500种植物
contain over 1,500 species of plant,
但是有些资源很难获取
but some are very difficult to get at...
甚至是最聪明的动物之一
...even for one of the most intelligent of animals.
黑猩猩
Chimpanzees.
这群中的长者知道哪里可以找到最营养的食物
The elders in this group know where to find the most nutritious food
以及如何提取其中的养分
and how to extract it.
这些年轻幼崽要生存到成年
But if they are to survive to adulthood,
必须向父母学习这些技能
the youngsters must learn these skills from their parents.
这个年轻的雌性五岁
This young female is five years old...
这个年纪，可以学到一堂重要的课
...old enough to be given an important lesson.
这是传授知识的老师
And this is her teacher.
她妈妈
Her mother.
该课程是如何破解坚果
The lesson is how to crack a nut.
熟练使用工具是一项复杂的技能
Using tools like this is so complex
目前仅由少数黑猩猩群体掌握
that it has only been mastered by a handful of chimpanzee communities.
这是黑猩猩已经实践了数千年的技能
This is a skill that has been practised by chimps for several thousand years.
是时候自己尝试一下了
Time to try for herself.
她需要找到更好的工具
She needs to find a better tool.
小石块的撞击力明显不够强
Small rocks just don't have the clout.
而大的则过于笨重
And larger ones are too cumbersome.
木头貌似既轻又结实
Wood is both light and strong...
但力度又不够
...but not strong enough.
回来再看看老师吧
Back to teacher.
年轻的黑猩猩可能要花十年
It may take a young chimp up to a decade to perfect
才能完美破解坚果所需的技能
the skills it needs for nut-cracking.
但是她已经掌握了一件本领
But she's already mastered one thing.
当她的手指无法触及里面的果仁时
When her fingers can't reach the nut inside...
她会折下树枝，适当调整
...she strips down a branch to size...
宛若汤匙
...and makes herself a spoon.
一生中将学习使用许多工具
She'll learn to use many tools in her life...
最终，她将分享这些知识
...and eventually she'll share this knowledge
给自己的幼崽
with youngsters of her own,
使后代能够收获雨林家园的食物资源
enabling them to harvest the riches of their rainforest home.
雨林中生活的丰富多样
The sheer abundance of life in the rainforests
非洲大陆东部的生存方式毫不逊色
is rivalled by that on the eastern side of the continent.
东非大裂谷纵观南北，全长6500公里
The Great Rift Valley runs for 4,000 miles down the length of Africa.
形成于大约在三千万年前
It developed some 30 million years ago,
地壳板块运动，当时一股巨大的熔岩
when a giant plume of molten rock pushing up from the depths
从深处推裂开了地壳
cracked the Earth's crust apart.
淡水逐渐聚集在这个裂口的地板上
Fresh water began to accumulate on the floor of this rift...
形成了一系列湖泊
...and a chain of lakes developed.
这些湖泊现在是最丰富的淡水栖息地之一
These lakes are now one of the richest freshwater habitats
随处可见
to be found anywhere.
一个独特鱼类家族，慈鲷
One single family of fish here - the cichlids -
已经演变成1,500多种不同的品种
has evolved into more than 1,500 different species.
这看起来像天堂
This might look like paradise,
其实这些慈鲷物种之间的竞争非常激烈
but competition between these cichlid species is intense.
这个拥挤的世界危机四伏
This crowded world is a dangerous one.
毕竟，幼鱼可是不错的美味
Baby fish, after all, make a tasty meal.
因此，许多慈鲷妈妈已经进化出一套非常有效的育儿措施
So, many cichlid mothers have developed a very effective way
保护后代的安全
of keeping their offspring safe.
他们用嘴当流动托儿所
They use their mouths as a mobile nursery.
这是一个安全的避风港，鱼苗可以留在这里，直到危险过去
It's a safe haven where the fry can stay until danger has passed.
当危机解除，妈妈释放出它们
When the coast is clear, she releases them.
慈鲷雌性开始这种行为源于
This kind of behaviour starts when the cichlid female
她刚产下卵时 便将其放在嘴里以确保安全
picks up her newly laid eggs and holds them in her mouth to keep them safe.
在繁殖季节，雄性慈鲷闪烁着黄色的尾巴斑点
During spawning, her mate flashes his yellow tail spots
鼓励雌性持续产蛋
to encourage her to keep laying.
产出的卵
As each batch of eggs emerges,
慈鲷妈妈迅速含在口中
she scoops them up.
但是这对慈鲷的举动在被监视到了
But this couple are being watched...
这就是密点歧须鮠
...by cuckoo catfish.
密点歧须鮠成群结队地扫荡
They work as a gang
肆意吞食能发现的慈鲷卵
and devour as many cichlid eggs as they can find.
在一批嘈杂和混乱中
Then, in the middle of all this activity,
其中一只密点歧须鮠也开始产卵
one of the catfish also spawns.
慈鲷妈妈匆忙收集所有她能看见的卵
The cichlid mother collects every egg she can see.
现在，她要慢慢等待
Now, by herself, she must wait
嘴里的卵发育成熟
while the eggs in her mouth develop.
这需要三个星期
It will take three weeks.
这期间她一直没有吃东西
She doesn't eat throughout that entire time.
但是18天后
But 18 days later,
情况好像不太对劲
something is not right.
慈鲷妈妈竟然把没有发育好的卵吐了出来
The female blows out her young before they're fully ready to emerge.
然后是密点歧须鮠的幼鱼...
And they are followed by young cuckoo catfish...
个头是慈鲷婴儿的三倍
...three times the size of her own babies.
她的嘴里可能有多达六条密点歧须鮠
She may have as many as six of them in her mouth.
现在
And now
他们开始抢食慈鲷宝宝
they begin to eat the cichlid babies.
慈鲷妈妈把密点歧须鮠当成了自己亲生的孩子
The female cichlid treats the baby catfish as if they were hers.
它们是鱼类中的“杜鹃”
They are truly cuckoos among fish!
曾经鬼斧神工创造大裂谷的自然力量
The forces that created the Great Rift Valley
至今仍在塑造非洲的地貌
continue to shape Africa's landscape
即使在今天
even today.
在地壳的薄弱部位，熔融岩石继续喷发
At weak spots in the Earth's crust, molten rock continues to erupt.
非洲大陆上有200座火山...
There are some 200 volcanoes on the continent...
...其中许多活跃
...many of them active.
他们可能带来破坏
They may bring destruction
最终会成为生息之地
but also, eventually, fertility.
这是 伦盖伊火山
This is Ol Doinyo Lengai.
在过去的40万年中，喷发的火山灰
For the past 400,000 years, ash from this great volcano
撒落在塞伦盖蒂的热带稀树草原上
has fallen on the surrounding savannas of the Serengeti
并大大丰富了沃土
and greatly enriched them.
这是非洲大陆上最好的牧场
This is the best grazing on the continent.
这是世界上最大的迁徙动物群体
On it live the world's largest herds of migrating animals...
反过来 这个群体供养着各种捕食者
...and they, in turn, support predators.
在肯尼亚，猎豹已经形成了不同寻常的联盟
Here, in Kenya, cheetahs have formed an unusual alliance.
这些最快的猫科动物，通常两三只结伴捕猎
These swiftest of cats usually hunt in groups of two or three.
但是这是五搭档，是有记录以来最大的猎豹群体
But this team of five is one of the largest ever recorded.
其中包括两对兄弟
Two sets of brothers
还有一只雄性首领
and a lead male.
它们已经在一起生活和狩猎了将近三年
They have now lived and hunted together for almost three years.
通过合作，他们可以保持
By teaming up, they can hold
占据该地区最好的领土
the best territory in the area.
但即使这样，要供养五口成员，每次狩猎都至关重要
But, even so, with five mouths to feed, every hunt is very important.
他们已经三天没吃到食物
They haven't eaten for three days.
为了获取猎物，他们必须距离围捕场30米以内
To make a kill, they must get within 30 metres of their quarry
没有被发现
without being detected.
灌木丛遮蔽
Thick cover.
会帮助他们
That will help them.
转角牛羚几乎是猎豹的三倍
Topi - nearly three times their size...
牛羚身体强壮足够击退狮子
...and quite strong enough to fight off a lion,
更不用说一个猎豹了
let alone a single cheetah.
正在开阔地带
Now out in the open...
猎豹走的每一步都增加了他们成功的机会
...every step the cheetahs take increases their chance of success.
牛群四散而逃，猎豹分头追击
The herd scatter, and the team splits up.
但是他们距离目标还是不够近
But they didn't get close enough.
他们将目标切换到斑马
They switch targets to zebra.
现在草原上已经都知道猎豹在这里了
Everyone now knows that they're here.
他们必须调整捕猎战术
They must devise a different approach.
所有的目光都提防着猎豹兄弟
All eyes are on the brothers.
开阔地带，它们似乎没有威胁
Out in the open, they seem to be no threat.
雄性首领也不见踪影
But the lead male is missing.
猎豹兄弟负责迷惑敌人
The brothers are decoys.
陷阱已设置
The trap is set.
现在，其他四个人加入队伍
The other four now join the lead male.
在五头猎豹的联合攻击下
Under the combined weight of five cheetah,
猎物很快丧命
death comes quickly.
非洲的稀树草原供养着大型食草群体
Today, Africa's savannas support larger herds of big game
比世界上任何其他地方都多
than anywhere else in the world.
他们以不同的方式
And they, one way or another,
为各种小型动物提供食物
provide food for all kinds of smaller creatures.
一只牛椋鸟
An oxpecker.
一只足智多谋的小鸟，拥有独特的进食习性
A resourceful little bird with an unusual diet.
对他们来说，跳蚤和蜱虫等寄生虫
Fleas, ticks and even dandruff are food,
甚至皮屑都是美味
as far as they are concerned.
双方受益
Both parties benefit.
牛椋鸟能够饱餐一顿
The oxpecker gets a good meal...
那些自己无法够到的地方 得到了清理
...and the host is cleaned in those places it could never reach for itself.
一只牛椋鸟每天吃掉数百只蜱虫
Each bird, every day, collects hundreds of ticks
和成千上万的昆虫幼虫
and thousands of insect larvae.
甚至有些牛椋鸟会更加冒险
But some oxpeckers go for rather riskier meals.
河马具有很强的领土意识，而且残暴
Hippopotamus are highly territorial and very aggressive...
牛椋鸟必须时刻保持警惕
...so oxpeckers tackling them must always be on their guard.
但它的收获不止于此
But there's much to be gained.
血液是最有营养的食物
Blood is the most nutritious meal of all.
它们不停啄食避免伤口愈合，让血液不断流出
Pecking ensures that cuts remain open and blood keeps flowing.
牛椋鸟一旦发现伤口，便会紧跟不舍
And an oxpecker, once it's found an open wound,
根本不管寄主有多恼火
will stay alongside it, no matter how much that irritates its host.
好处是什么呢
The reward? An endless supply of food,
不管条件如何，都有血液供应
whatever the conditions.
并非整个非洲处处都富饶
Not all of Africa is rich and fertile.
这片大陆的三分之一是沙漠
A third of the continent is desert.
这是西南的纳米布沙漠
This is the Namib in the southwest.
在沙漠的中心，有一处70年前就废弃的
At its heart, a disused diamond mine
钻石矿
that was abandoned nearly 70 years ago.
但是这里还生活着一个居民
But it still has one inhabitant.
一位沙漠专家
A desert specialist...
也是非洲最罕见的掠食者之一
...and one of Africa's rarest predators.
棕色的鬣狗
The brown hyena.
这个鬼城是她的家
This ghost town is her home.
废墟保护她免受风吹日晒
Its ruins give her valuable protection from the elements.
她来这里已经15年了
She has been here for 15 years.
她已经饲养了九代幼崽
She's already reared nine generations of cubs.
这两个幼年鬣狗已经步入生命中的关键阶段
These two youngsters have reached a critical stage in their lives.
只有四个月大，需要不断获得固体食物
They're four months old, and now they need regular solid food.
但这些废墟中，没有可食用的东西，
But there is nothing edible in these ruins,
棕鬣狗妈妈要去别的地方觅食
so their mother has to look elsewhere
而且可能一去就是数几天
and may leave them for several days on end.
棕色鬣狗每天可能会走30多公里以寻找食物
Brown hyenas may walk over 20 miles a day in search of food.
这里称得上是我们星球上最为恶劣的环境之一
This is some of the most hostile country on the planet.
温度高达50摄氏度
Temperatures reach a blistering 50 degrees Celsius.
强风不断吹来
Strong winds blow incessantly.
纳米布的鬣狗从四面八方前往沙丘与大海的交汇处
Hyenas from all over the Namib head for where the sand dunes meet the sea.
绵延的沙滩
Somewhere along
这看似贫瘠荒凉
this seemingly barren stretch of sand,
但有的地方，存在大量食物
there is food in great quantity.
南非海狗
Cape fur seals.
这里大约有一万只
There are around 10,000 of them here.
成年南非海狗大而结实
Adult seals are large and strong.
但是他们的小崽都是幼小无力
But their pups are neither.
南非海狗妈妈们严密监护着
The youngsters are closely guarded by their mothers.
而棕鬣狗知道这需要耐心
A hyena, however, knows to be patient.
南非海豹妈妈们必须回到海中降温
Sooner or later, seal mothers must return to the ocean to cool off.
一只海狗幼崽可以喂鬣狗和她的家人几天
A single seal pup could feed a hyena and her family for days.
但是找到食物只是成功的一半
But finding food is only half the battle.
现在必须将食物安全带回
It now has to be carried back.
胡狼早已闻风而至
A jackal is here too...
而且也不是孤身一只
...and it's not alone.
如果棕鬣狗失去食物，她将不能养育幼崽
If a hyena loses her kill, she'll have nothing with which to feed her cubs.
胡狼在海岸活动，不会纠缠很远
The jackals won't follow her very far from the coast.
沙漠内部，对他们来说太热了
It's too hot for them in the desert interior.
经过这些漫长的旅程
Only by making these long journeys
棕鬣狗能在纳米布的中间生存吗？
can brown hyenas manage to survive in the middle of the Namib.
但是有些沙漠动物很少出远门
But some desert animals seldom move far.
卡拉哈里沙漠
The Kalahari Desert.
这里的食物非常充足
Here, food is more plentiful...
但是都是隐藏的很深
...but it's hidden.
穿山甲
A pangolin.
她可以捕获其他动物无法获得的食物
She can collect food that others can't reach.
敏锐的嗅觉使她能够发现沙子下面的蚁巢
A keen sense of smell enables her to detect
挖掘蚂蚁和白蚁
the presence of ants and termites in their nests beneath the sand.
它的舌头很粘，长约30厘米，
Her sticky tongue, some 30cm long,
能够从地下深处舔食到蚂蚁
enables her to collect them from deep underground.
它的举动在密切监控之下
And she's being carefully watched.
天气越干燥，白蚁的巢穴就越深
The drier it gets, the deeper the termites live.
许多甚至是穿山甲所不能及的
Many are way beyond the reach of even a pangolin.
但是这难不倒土豚
But not of an aardvark.
土豚是世界上最大的穴居动物
It's the world's largest burrowing animal.
它的嗅觉极为敏锐
Its sense of smell is extremely acute.
铲状的爪子和有力的腿使其能够向下挖掘
Shovel-like claws and powerful legs enable it to dig down
达到五到六米的深度
to depths of five or six metres.
一个成年的土豚每天需要吃掉约五万只白蚁
A full-grown aardvark needs to eat about 50,000 termites every day.
白蚁营养丰富，水分充沛，
Termites are highly nutritious and full of moisture,
可以在这里全年都可以找到
and they can be collected here year round.
土豚通常是夜间活动
Aardvark are usually nocturnal.
但这只土豚是在白天觅食
But the fact that this one is foraging in daylight
说明当地食物十分匮乏
is a sign that food is scarce.
卡拉哈里最近的干旱导致白蚁数量减少
Recent droughts in the Kalahari have led to low termite numbers
结果，这里的土豚深受其害 濒临饿死
and, as a consequence, aardvarks here are close to starvation.
全球气候变化，正在影响非洲的许多动物的命运
Changes in the world's climate are affecting many of Africa's animals.
根据预测 到下个世纪
It's predicted that in the next century,
南非的气温升高将是全球平均升幅的两倍
Southern Africa will warm twice as much as the global average.
对于那些无法快速适应者而言，未来将是希望渺茫
The future will be bleak for those that cannot adapt fast enough.
津巴布韦已经六个月没有下雨了
In Zimbabwe, it hasn't rained in six months.
干旱期间，食物变得越来越难找
During a drought, food becomes harder and harder to find.
微白相思树的荚果中富含蛋白质
Apple-ring acacias produce pods that are full of protein...
但大都挂在高高的枝头
...but mostly on their higher branches.
荚果距离地面大约六米
Six metres up, they're out of reach,
即使是非洲大陆上最大的动物也够不到
even for the continent's largest animals.
这头公象每天需要吃掉约90公斤的植物
This bull elephant needs to eat about 90kg of vegetation every day.
他发展出了一套独特的生存方法
He's worked out a remarkable way of surviving
用来度过食物匮乏时期
in these lean times.
但这需要消耗巨大的体力
But it requires great physical strength.
能掌握这项技能的公象也是寥寥无几
Only a handful of bulls have mastered the skill.
重达五吨多
He weighs over five tonnes.
这是一项非凡的尝试
This is a truly monumental effort.
他周围的动物也是受益匪浅
Those around him benefit too.
大象利用自己的才智帮助它们生存
Elephants have used their great intelligence to help them survive
度过非洲几千年来最干旱的时期
Africa's driest times for millennia.
但是今天，他们面临着更大的威胁
But today, they face an even greater threat.
据认为，曾经有多达两千万头大象生活在非洲
It's thought that as many as 20 million elephants once roamed the continent,
后来许多是因为象牙而被杀害
but many have been killed for their tusks...
而象牙仅仅用于装饰为目的
...their ivory used for entirely ornamental purposes.
如今非洲仅存35万头大象
Now just 350,000 elephants remain.
这些被没收牙库，让人触目惊心
These stockpiles of confiscated tusks
这些仅是在短短一年内
represent half of the elephants killed on the continent
非洲大陆遇害大象数量的一半
in just one year.
但是在非洲所现存的的野生动物中
But of all of Africa's remaining wildlife,
受到盗猎影响最大的是犀牛
it is the rhinoceros that has been most affected by poaching.
在远东地区，犀牛角被用作传统药物
In the Far East, its horn is used as traditional medicine.
非洲所有的犀牛现在都受到威胁
All of Africa's rhinos are now under threat...
但是对于其中一个犀牛亚种来说，可能已经为时已晚
...but for one subspecies, it's likely to be already too late.
北白犀牛正面临灭绝
The northern white rhinoceros is facing extinction.
科学家们正在研究解决方案，
Scientists are working on a solution,
但是现在已经没有雄性的北白犀牛，自然繁殖是不可能的
but no male now survives, so natural breeding is impossible.
这两头是仅存的北白犀
These two females are the last of their kind.
当他们死后
When they die,
在地球上曾经生存数百万年的北白犀牛亚种
an entire subspecies that inhabited the Earth for millions of years
将永远消失
will have disappeared for ever.
在整个非洲大地
Right across Africa,
人类活动对所有野生动植物造成毁灭性影响
human beings are having a devastating impact on all wildlife.
猎豹数量每年都在减少
Cheetah numbers are decreasing
year on year.
如今，非洲大陆上还剩下不到八千只猎豹
Today, there are fewer than 8,000 left on the continent.
人们将穿山甲鳞片用于传统医学的需求
The global demand for pangolin scales for use in traditional medicine
现在使它们成为地球上非法走私最多的动物
has now made them the most trafficked animal on the planet.
西非黑猩猩受到栖息地丧失的威胁
And western chimpanzees are so threatened by the loss of their habitat
他们现在的处境岌岌可危，已经被列入极度濒危
that they are now critically endangered.
在这只雌性的生命历程中
In this female's lifetime,
科特迪瓦有四分之三的森林遭到砍伐
three-quarters of the forest in the Ivory Coast
用于种植农作物
has been felled for plantations.
砍伐森林并不是非洲的特有现象
Deforestation - and not only in Africa -
目前仍在大规模持续发生
continues on an enormous scale.
如今 每年毁坏2600完公顷的森林
64 million acres of forest are destroyed every year
用于发展农业和工业
to make way for agriculture and industry.
这意味着，每秒钟就有相当于
An area of forest the size of a football field
一片足球场大小的森林消失
is disappearing every second.
气候变化正在改变全球天气模式
Climate change is affecting global weather patterns.
降雨越来越不可预测
Rainfall is increasingly unpredictable.
全球平均气温在飙升
Average temperatures are soaring all over the globe.
极端天气频频出现
Extreme weather is now affecting wildlife
七大洲的野生动物都受影响
on all seven of the planet's continents.
如今，许多科学家警告，我们正处于物种大灭绝的开始
Today, scientists tell us that we are at the start of a mass extinction,
而这一切都有归结于人类活动
and one that is being caused by human activity.
超过一百万种从地球永久消失
Over a million species could be wiped out,
有些可能就发生在未来几十年内
many within the next few decades.
如果有人类帮助，即使是最脆弱的野生动植物种群仍然可以恢复
But with help, even the most vulnerable wildlife populations can still recover.
在非洲的维龙加国家公园，
In Africa's Virunga National Park,
一项针对山地大猩猩的强化保护计划
an intensive conservation programme for the mountain gorilla
使得它们的数量，自记录开始以来，首次超过1000只
has raised their numbers above 1,000 for the first time since records began.
在南极洲
And in Antarctica,
国际捕鲸禁令的颁布意味着这些庞然大物
the international ban on whaling has meant that the great whales
已经开始重返南极
have returned to the Southern Ocean in numbers not seen for a century.
数量之多百年难遇
So we can improve things...
所以我们只要下定决心
...if we determine to do so.
就可以改写
This is a crucial moment in time.
我们现在做出的决定
The decisions we take now
将影响动物，人类的未来，
will influence the future of animals, humanity,
甚至地球上的所有生命
and indeed all life on Earth.